<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="yes"?>
<infomlFile xsi:schemaLocation="http://infoml.org/infomlFile     http://infoml.org/s/infomlFile.xsd" xmlns="http://infoml.org/infomlFile" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance">
    <infoml cardId="gw667_090906221121053" encoding="UTF-8" version="0.90">
        <data>
            <pointers>
                <ptr targetId="gw667_090815161114586"/>
                <ptr targetId="gw667_090815162059614"/>
                <ptr targetId="gw667_090815163031398"/>
                <ptr targetId="gw667_090815164115403"/>
            </pointers>
        </data>
    </infoml>
    <infoml cardId="gw667_090815161114586" encoding="UTF-8" version="0.90">
        <data>
            <title>the ability to think</title>
            <content exact="true">
                <p>What makes a strange loop appear in a brain and not in a video feedback system, then, is an _ability_--the ability to think--which is, in effect, a one-syllable word standing for the possession of a sufficiently large repertoire of true triggerable symbols.</p>
            </content>
            <source>
                <agent role="card creator">
                    <first>Gregg</first>
                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                </agent>
                <agent role="author">
                    <first>Douglas</first>
                    <middle>R.</middle>
                    <surname>Hofstadter</surname>
                </agent>
                <container>
                    <containerNamePart>I Am a Strange Loop</containerNamePart>
                    <date role="publication">2007</date>
                </container>
                <location>
                    <point unit="page" value=" 203"/>
                </location>
            </source>
        </data>
        <selectors>
            <tag>strangeloops</tag>
            <tag>thinking</tag>
            <tag>triggerable</tag>
            <tag>patterns</tag>
            <tag>abilities</tag>
        </selectors>
        <properties>
            <dateCreated>2009-09-06</dateCreated>
        </properties>
    </infoml>
    <infoml cardId="gw667_090815162059614" encoding="UTF-8" version="0.90">
        <data>
            <title>to label, categorize, and find precedents</title>
            <content exact="true">
                <p>My brain (and yours, too, dear reader) is constantly seeking to label, to categorize, to find precedents and analogues--in other words, _to simplify while not letting essence slip away_. It carries on this activity relentlessly, not only in response to freshly arriving sensory input but also in response to its own internal dance, and there really is not much of a difference between the two cases, for once sensory input has gotten beyond the retina or the tympani or the skin, it enters the realm of the _internal_, and from that point on, perception is solely an internal affair.</p>
            </content>
            <source>
                <agent role="card creator">
                    <first>Gregg</first>
                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                </agent>
                <agent role="author">
                    <first>Douglas</first>
                    <middle>R.</middle>
                    <surname>Hofstadter</surname>
                </agent>
                <container>
                    <containerNamePart>I Am a Strange Loop</containerNamePart>
                    <date role="publication">2007</date>
                </container>
                <location>
                    <point unit="page" value="297"/>
                </location>
            </source>
        </data>
        <selectors>
            <tag>categorzing</tag>
            <tag>precedence</tag>
            <tag>analogues</tag>
            <tag>brain</tag>
            <tag>sensory input</tag>
            <tag>sense organs</tag>
            <tag>perception</tag>
        </selectors>
        <properties>
            <dateCreated>2009-09-06</dateCreated>
        </properties>
    </infoml>
    <infoml cardId="gw667_090815163031398" encoding="UTF-8" version="0.90">
        <data>
            <title>"I" is an outcome, not a starting point</title>
            <content exact="true">
                <p>It's a subtle idea whose crux is that what you call "I" is an _outcome_, not a starting point. You've coalesced in an unplanned fashion, coming only slowly into existence, not in a flash. At the beginning, when the brain that would later house your soul was taking form, there was no you. But that brain slowly grew, and its experiences slowly accumulated. Somewhere along the way, as more and more things happened to it, were registered by it, and became internalized in it, it started imitating the cultural and linguistic conventions in which it was immersed, and thus it tentatively said "I" about itself (even though the referent of that word was still blurry). That's roughly when it noticed it was somewhere--and not surprisingly, it was where a certain brain was! At that point, though, it didn't know anything about its brain. What it knew instead was its brain's _container_, which was a certain body. But even though it didn't know anything about its brain, that nascent "I" faithfully followed its brain around just as a shadow always tags along after a moving object.</p>
            </content>
            <notes1>
                <p>Part of one of the author's dialogues between two people holding opposing viewpoints</p>
            </notes1>
            <source>
                <agent role="card creator">
                    <first>Gregg</first>
                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                </agent>
                <agent role="author">
                    <first>Douglas</first>
                    <middle>R.</middle>
                    <surname>Hofstadter</surname>
                </agent>
                <container>
                    <containerNamePart>I Am a Strange Loop</containerNamePart>
                    <date role="publication">2007</date>
                </container>
                <location>
                    <point unit="page" value="284"/>
                </location>
            </source>
        </data>
        <selectors>
            <tag>brain</tag>
            <tag>"I"</tag>
            <tag>causality</tag>
            <tag>evolution</tag>
            <tag>soul</tag>
            <tag>self</tag>
            <tag>being</tag>
        </selectors>
        <properties>
            <dateCreated>2009-09-06</dateCreated>
        </properties>
    </infoml>
    <infoml cardId="gw667_090815164115403" encoding="UTF-8" version="0.90">
        <data>
            <title>the illusion of "I"</title>
            <content exact="true">
                <p>The problem is that in a sense, an "I" is something created out of nothing. And since making something out of nothing is never possible, the alleged something turns out to be an illusion, in the end, but a very powerful one, like the?? marble among the envelopes....</p>
                <p>One thing that gives many people a sneaking suspicion is that something about this "I" notion might be mythical was precisely what you've been troubled about all through our discussion--namely, there seems to be something incompatible between the hard laws of physics and the existence of vague, shadowy things called "I"'s....</p>
                <p>A second hint that something needs revision has to do with what we perceive as causing what. In our everyday life, we take it for granted that an "I" can cause things, can push things around. If I decide to drive to the grocery store, my one-ton automobile winds up taking me there and bringing me back. Now that seems pretty peculiar in the world of physics, where everything comes about solely as a result of how particles interact. How does the particle story leave room for a shadowy, ethereal "I" to cause a heavy car to move somewhere? This, too, casts a bit of doubt on the reality of the notion of "I".</p>
            </content>
            <notes1>
                <p>Part of one of the author's dialogues between two people holding opposing viewpoints</p>
            </notes1>
            <source>
                <agent role="card creator">
                    <first>Gregg</first>
                    <surname>Williams</surname>
                </agent>
                <agent role="author">
                    <first>Douglas</first>
                    <middle>R.</middle>
                    <surname>Hofstadter</surname>
                </agent>
                <container>
                    <containerNamePart>I Am a Strange Loop</containerNamePart>
                    <date role="publication">2007</date>
                </container>
                <location>
                    <range begin="292" end="293" unit="page"/>
                </location>
            </source>
        </data>
        <selectors>
            <tag>"I "</tag>
            <tag>illusions</tag>
            <tag>self</tag>
            <tag>physics</tag>
            <tag>self</tag>
            <tag>physical objects</tag>
        </selectors>
        <properties>
            <dateCreated>2009-09-06</dateCreated>
        </properties>
    </infoml>
</infomlFile>

